[Music]
Reedman
reads the Giver by Lois Lowry narrated by Fraser Reedman chapter
11 Jonas felt nothing unusual at first.
He felt only the light touch of the old man's hands on his back. He tried to
relax, to breathe evenly. The room was absolutely silent, and for a moment Jonas
feared that he might disgrace himself now, on the first day of his training, by falling
asleep. Then he shivered. He realized that the touch of the hands felt, suddenly,
cold. At the same instant, breathing in, he felt the air change, and his very breath was
cold. He licked his lips, and in doing so, his tongue touched the suddenly chilled
air. It was very startling; but he was not at all frightened, now. He was filled with energy,
and he breathed again, feeling the sharp intake of frigid air. Now, too, he could
feel cold air swirling around his entire body. He felt it blow against his hands
where they lay at his sides, and over his back. The touch of the man's hand seemed
to have disappeared. Now he became aware of an entire L new
sensation pin Pricks No, because they were soft and without paint Tiny, cold
feather-like feelings peppered his body and face. He put out his tongue again, and
caught one of the dots of cold upon it.
It disappeared from his awareness instantly; but he caught another, and
another. The sensation made him smile. One part of his consciousness knew that he
was still lying there, on the bed, in the Annex room. Yet another, separate part of
his being was upright now, in a sitting position, and beneath him he could feel
that he was not on the soft decorated bed covering at
all rather seated on a flat, hard surface.
His hands now held (though at the same time they were still motionless at his
sides) a rough, damp rope. And he could see, though his eyes
were closed. He could see a bright, whirling torrent of crystals in the air
around him, and he could see them gather on the backs of his hands, like cold
fur. His breath was visible. Beyond, through the swirl of what he now, somehow,
perceived was the thing the old man had spoken of—
snow —he could look out and down a great distance it was up high
someplace ground was thick with the furry snow, but he sat slightly above it on a hard, flat
object. Sled, he knew abruptly. He was sitting on a thing
called sled. And the sled itself seemed to be poised at the top of a long,
extended mound that rose from the very land where he was. Even as he thought the
word "mound," his new consciousness told him hill. Then sled, with Jonas himself
upon it, began to move through the snowfall, and he understood instantly that now he was going
downhill. No voice made an explanation.
The experience explained itself to him. His face cut through the frigid air as he began the
descent, moving through the substance called snow on the vehicle called sled,
which propelled itself on what he now knew without doubt to be runners.
Comprehending all of those things as he sped downward, he was free to enjoy the
breathless glee that overwhelmed him: the speed, the clear cold air, the total
silence, the feeling of balance and excitement and peace.
Then, as the angle of incline lessened, as the mound— —the hill —flattened, nearing the
bottom sled's forward motion slowed. The snow was piled now around it, and he
pushed with his body, moving it forward, not wanting the exhilarating ride to end.
Finally the obstruction of the piled snow was too much for the thin runners
of the sled, and he came to a stop. He sat there for a moment, panting,
holding the rope in his cold hands.
Tentatively he opened his eyes— —not his Snow Hill sled eyes but they had been
opened throughout the strange ride. He opened his ordinary eyes, and saw that he
was still on the bed, that he had not moved at
all. The old man, still beside the bed, was watching
him. "How do you feel?" he asked. Jonas sat up and tried to answer
honestly. "Surprised," he said, after a moment.
The old man wiped his forehead with his sleeve phw he
said. "It was exhausting. But you know, even transmitting that tiny memory to you— —I
think it lightened me just a little." "Do you mean— —you did say I could ask
questions?" The man nodded, encouraging his question. "Do you mean that now you don't
have the memory of it— —of that ride on the sled— —anymore?" "That's right little weight off
this old body it was such fun! And now you don't
have it anymore! I took it from you!" But the old man
laughed. "All I gave you was one ride, on
one sled, in one snow, on one hill. I have
a whole world of them in my memory. I could give them to you one by one, a
thousand times, and there would still be more." "Are you saying that I— —I mean we—
—could do it again?" Jonas asked. "I'd really like to. I think I could steer, by pulling
the rope. I didn't try this time, because it was so
new." The old man, laughing, shook his head.
"Maybe another day, for a treat. But there's no time, really, just to play. I
only wanted to begin by showing you how it works. "Now," he said, turning businesslike,
"lie back down. I want to—" Jonas did. He was eager for whatever experience would come
next. But he had, suddenly, so many questions. "Why don't we have snow, and
sleds, and hills?" he asked. "And when did we, in the past? Did my parents have sleds
when they were young? Did you?" The old man shrugged and gave a short laugh. "No," he
told Jonas. "It's a very distant memory.
That's why it was so exhausting— —I had to tug it forward for many generations
back. It was given to me when I was a newer Receiver, and the previous Receiver
had to pull it through a long time period, too." "But what happened to those
things? Snow, and the rest of it?" "Climate Control. Snow made growing
food difficult, limited the agricultural periods. And unpredictable weather made
transportation almost impossible at times. It wasn't a practical thing, so it
became obsolete when we went to Sameness. "And hills, too," he added. "They
made conveyance of goods unwieldy. Trucks; buses. Slowed them down.
So—" He waved his hand, as if a gesture that caused hills to disappear.
"Sameness," he concluded. Jonas frowned. "I wish we had those things, still.
Just now and then."' The old man smiled. "So do I," he said. "But that choice
is not ours."
"But sir Jonah suggested, "since you have so much power—" The man corrected him.
"Honor," he said firmly. "I have great honor.
So will you. But you will find that that is not the same as
power. "Lie quietly now. Since we've entered into the topic of climate I'm
going to give you something else. And this time I'm not going to tell you the
name of it cuz I want to test the receiving. You should be able to proce
receive the name without being told. I gave away snow and sled and
downhill and runners by telling them to you in advance." Without being instructed,
Jonas closed his eyes again. He felt the hands on his back again. He waited. Now it
came more quickly, the feelings. This time the hands didn't become cold, but instead
began to feel warm on his body. They moistened a little. The warmth spread,
extending across his shoulders, up his neck, onto the side of his
face. He could feel it through his clothed parts, too: a pleasant all over
sensation; and when he licked his lips this time, the air was hot and
heavy. He didn't move. There was no sled. His posture didn't
change. He was simply alone someplace, out of doors, lying down, and the warmth came from far
above was not as exciting as the ride through the snowy air; but it was pleasurable and
comforting. Suddenly he perceived the word for it: sunshine. He perceived that it came from the
sky. Then it ended. "Sunshine," he said aloud, opening his
eyes. "Good. You did get the word. That makes my job easier. Not so much explaining."
"And it came from the sky." "That's right," the old man said. "Just the way it used
to." "Before Sameness. Before Climate Control," Jonas added. The man laughed. "You
receive well, and learn quickly. I'm very pleased with you. That's enough for today, I think.
We're off to a good start." There was a question bothering Jonas. "Sir," he
said, "The Chief Elder told me— —she told everyone— —and you told me, too, that it
would be painful. So I was a little scared. But it didn't hurt at all. I
really enjoyed it." He looked quizzically at the old man. The man
sighed. "I started you with memories of pleasure. My previous failure gave me the wisdom to do
that." He took a few deep breaths. "Jonas," he said, "it will be painful.
But it need not be painful yet." "I'm brave. I really am." Jonas sat up a little
straighter. The old man looked at him for a moment. He smiled. "I can see that," he
said. "Well, since you asked the question— —I think I have enough energy
for one more transmission.
"Lie down once more. This will be the last today." Jonas obeyed
cheerfully. He closed his eyes, waiting, and felt the hands again; then he felt
the warmth again, the sunshine again, coming from the sky of this other
consciousness that was so new to him. This time, as he lay basking in the
wonderful warmth, he felt the passage of time. His real self was aware that it was
only a minute or two; but his other memory receiving self felt hours pass in the
sun. His skin began to sting. Restlessly he moved one arm, bending it, and felt a
sharp pain in the crease of his inner arm at the
elbow. "Ouch," he said loudly, and shifted on the bed ow he said, wincing at the
shift, and even moving his mouth to speak made his face
hurt. He knew there was a word, but the pain kept him from grasping it. Then it
ended. He opened his eyes, wincing with discomfort. "It hurt," he told the mat and I
couldn't get the word for it." "It was sunburn," the old man told
him. "It hurt a lot Jonah said, "but I'm glad you gave it to me. It was
interesting. And now I understand better, what it meant, that there would be pain."
The man didn't respond. He sat silently for a second. Finally he said, "Get up, now. It's
time for you to go home." They both walked to the center of
the room. Jonas put his tunic back on. "Goodbye, sir," he said. "Thank you for my first
day." The old man nodded to him. He looked drained, and a little sad. "Sir?" Jonas said
shilly Yes? Do you have a question question?" "It's just that I don't know your
name. I thought you were The Receiver, but you say that now I'm The Receiver. So I
don't know what to call you." The man had sat back down in the comfortable
upholstered chair. He moved his shoulders around as if to ease away an aching
sensation. He seemed terribly weary. "Call me The Giver," he told Jonas
[Music]